College Hall Occupation Oral History Project, 1986
Smith College Archives
College Hall Occupation Oral History Project
1986
Smith College.
RG 80 UUID:a1d57e49-2512-4bf5-b4f5-7c92a6f0c22c
1 box (.75 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Student demonstration. Includes interviews and papers.
The College Hall Occupation Oral History Project was the work of two students enrolled in History 367b, Problems in American History: Autobiography, Biography, and Oral History in Twentieth Century America as taught by Maurice Isserman in spring 1986. The sixteen cassette tapes and two papers were given to the College Archives in the summer and fall of 1986 by the coordinators of the project, Donna Kenny '87 and Maureen Dooley Lawrence '87.
Feb. 20, Thursday Student/faculty rally and sit-in encouraging total divestment prior to the spring meeting of the Board of Trustees.
Feb. 22, Saturday Trustees choose not to adopt the divestment proposal set forth by the Senate Ethical Investment Committee.
Feb. 24, Monday "Round-the-clock" sit-in outside the President's office by circa 200 students and faculty to protest the Trustees' decision. Approximately 90 students spend the night in College Hall.
Feb. 25, Tuesday Approximately 150 students join the overnighters and 5:30 a.m. The protesters form human chains to block all entrances to College Hall. Employees are denied entrance to the building. President Dunn refuses to have the protesters arrested.
Feb. 26, Wednesday Protesters hold a press conference announcing their position and reading statements of support for the occupation. All-college meeting to discuss South Africa and the occupation of College Hall. Protesters send a group of "presidential delegates" to read a statement expressing their conviction that the takeover of College Hall was their only recourse.
Feb. 27, Thursday Protesters agree to negotiate with President Dunn. A small group of protesters begins a hunger strike.
Feb. 28, Friday Negotiations continue. Protesters hold a rally and announce the hunger strike to the public.
Mar. 1, Saturday An agreement is reached between President Dunn, the Board of Trustees, and the protesters.
Mar. 2, Sunday Occupation ends with a press conference and victory rally. Mar. 6, Thursday Required teach-in on South African-related issues and on relations between the Board of Trustees and the campus community.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
Donna Kenny's portion of the project consist of interviews with fourteen members of the administration, faculty, and staff and a paper based on the interviews. Many of these interviews are open for listening without restriction but in most cases permission from the interviewee is required before excerpts can be published in any way. Portions of Ms. Kenny's paper have been blocked out because she takes quotes from interviews that are restricted. Maureen Dooley Lawrence's portion of the project consists of four tapes of interviews with students participating in the occupation and a paper based on those interviews. All of the student interviews and Ms. Lawrence's paper are closed until July 1, 1991. At that time the tapes and paper will be made available with the names of the individuals removed.
History of the Collection
Search Terms
Smith College--Strikes, 1986.; Smith College--Students.; South Africa--Politics and government--1978-1989.; Kenny, Donna.; Lawrence, Maureen Dooley.; Isserman, Maurice.; Smith College.
Additional Information
Related Material
For a more detailed account of the occupation see the report prepared by the 1985-86 Committee on Community Policy (CCP) subcommittee dated October 1, 1986. See also issues of the student newspaper the Sophian during the spring of 1986 starting with the February 24th issue. The October, 23, 1986 issue followed the release of the CCP report. Additional material related to the occupation is available in the file on student demonstrations: 80.Dem 1986 CHO
- TAPE RECORDINGS
  - Mary Maples Dunn, President of the College Apr 18 1986, C165
    The interview is open for listening without restriction. Permission is required for publication or quotation in unpublished works.
  - Ann Burger, Dean of the College Mar 25 1986, C166
    Permission is required for listening, publication, or quotation in unpublished works.
  - Erica Bianchi-Jones, Secretary to the Board of Trustees. Mar 3 1986, C167
  - Philip Green, Professor of Government undated, C168
  - Maurice Isserman, Assistant Professor of History, Mar 25 1986; C169 Side A
  - Eleanor Rothman, Director of the Ada Comstock Scholars Program, Apr 1 1986; C169 Side B
    The interview is open for listening or quotation in unpublished works without restrictions. Permission to quote in published works must be obtained from the Smith College Archives.
  - Lisa Peck, Area Coordinator Mar 13 1986, C170
    The interview is open for listening, publication, or quotation in unpublished works without restrictions. Ms. Peck would like to receive a copy of any work which makes use of her interview.
  - Stanley Rothman, Professor of Government, Mar 7 1986; C171 Side A
    The interview is open for listening without restriction. Mr. Rothman must be notified before his interview is quoted in published or unpublished works.
  - Larry Selgelid, Treasurer of the College, Mar 10 1986; C171 Side B
  - Thomas Riddell, Assistant Professor of Economics, Mar 5 1986; C172 Side A
    The interview is open for listening or quotation in unpublished works without restrictions. Permission is required for publication.
  - Leo Weinstein, Professor of Government, Mar 6 1986; C172 Side B
  - Catherine "Kiki" Smith, Dean of the Freshman Class, undated; C173 Side A
  - Karen Pfeifer, Assistant Professor of Economics, undated; C173 Side B
    The interview is open for listening without restriction. Ms. Pfeifer must be notified regarding how the information is to be used. Permission is required for publication or quotation in unpublished works.
  - Frances Volkmann, Dean of the Faculty Mar 26 1986, C174
  - Teach-in Mar 6 1986, C175
  - Victory rally Mar 2 1986, C176
  - Student interviews, Feb-Mar 1986; C177 a-d
- PAPERS
  - Donna Kenny
    - Why Smith and Why Now? A Look at the Events of February 1986" May 2 1986
      (Portions of this paper are restricted because she takes quotes from interviews which are restricted.)
  - Maureen Dooley Lawrence
    - "It Happened at Smith" May 2 1986